Register of the David Brombart papers, 1917-2009
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject File, 1917-2009. (Box 8--19)
  - Islamic countries (Box 12)
    - Hassan Fathy Institute. Relates to efforts of the Hassan Fathy Institute, in conjunction with the International Construction Institute, to promote democratic construction trade unions in Islamic countries (Box 12)
      - Printed reports, 1988-2000 (Folder 12: 4)
        including Statement of Principles of the Hassan Fathy Institute; Early Deaths, Stunted Lives: The Hassan Fathy Project to Help Resolve the Global Housing Crisis (report to the United Nations General Assembly Special Session on Housing); and proceedings of the Hassan Fathy Institute Construction Workers Rights Symposium
      - Fathy, Hassan, Architecture for the Poor, (book), 1973 (Folder 12: 5)
    - Ibn Khaldun Society, 1995-2005. (Box 12)
      Relates to efforts of the Ibn Khaldun Society, in conjunction with the Institute of International Studies, to promote democracy in Islamic countries.
      - Correspondence with Khalid Durán, memoranda, and meeting and conference reports, 1995-2005 (Folder 12: 6)
      - Grant proposals to the National Endowment for Democracy and the U.S. Institute for Peace, 1997-1998 (Folder 13: 1)
      - TransState Islam issues, printed writings by Khalid Durán, and press coverage, 1995-2001 (Folder 13: 2)
  - Israel, 1965-1991. (Folder 13: 3)
    Includes Akiva Eger, The Role of Labour and Co-operation in the Development of Young States, 1965; and La coopération et les travailleurs au service du développement national, 1968
  - Joyce, John T. (president, International Construction Institute), 1991-2006. (Folder 13: 4)
    Includes correspondence; report to the AFL-CIO Executive Committee on the Persian Gulf War, 1991; and "The Challenge to the American Labor Movement," 2005 (typescript by Joyce)
  - Kahn, Thomas (director, AFL-CIO Department of International Affairs), 1960-2004. (Folder 13: 5)
    Includes Unfinished Revolution, 1960 (pamphlet by Kahn); memorial material upon the death of Kahn in 1992; and Rachelle Horowitz, "Tom Kahn and the Fight for Democracy: A Political Portrait and Personal Recollection," circa 2004
  - Kenya, 2006 (Folder 13: 6)
  - Kirkland, Lane (president, AFL-CIO) (Box 13)
  - General, 1973-2005 (Folder 13: 7)
  - Obituaries and memorial material, 1999 (Folder 13: 8)
  - Labor. (Box 14)
    Relates to international labor in general and especially to prospects for unification of international labor organizations
    - General, 1954-2007. (Folder 14: 1)
      Includes Jack Woddis, The Mask Is Off! 1954 (pamphlet); and Anthony Carew, "Free Trade Unionism in the International Context," 2002 (conference paper)
    - Internet printout, 2001-2009 (Folder 14: 2)
  - Labor-United States (Box 14)
    - General, 1951-2007. (Folder 14: 3)
      Mainly printed news stories. Includes joint statement by the American Federation of Labor, the Congress of Industrial Organizations and other unions, Equal Sacrifice for the Defense of America, 1951 (pamphlet)
    - Time magazine special issues on American labor, 1940-1947 (Folder 14: 4)
    - Cahn, William, A Pictorial History of American Labor, (book), 1972 (Folder 14: 5)
  - Labor and intelligence, 1974-2004. (Folder 15: 1)
    Printed matter relating to connections between labor organizations and the U.S. Central Intelligence Agency. Includes An Analysis of Our AFL-CIO Role in Latin America, or Under the Covers with the CIA, 1974 (pamphlet); and Anthony Carew, "The American Labor Movement in Fizzland: The Free Trade Union Committee and the CIA," 1998 (printed article)
  - Labor diplomacy, 1968-2007. (Folder 15: 2)
    Relates to the labor attaché program of the U.S. Department of State. Includes messages, memoranda and reports of the Department of State and the U.S. Department of Labor; and correspondence and reports of Anthony G. Freeman
  - Labor Research Association, 1986 (Folder 15: 3)
  - Lovestone, Jay (director, AFL-CIO Department of International Affairs) (Box 15)
    - General, 1953-2001. (Folder 15: 4)
      Includes photocopy of passport application by Lovestone, 1953; and photocopy of draft chapter from the book by Ted Morgan, A Covert Life: Jay Lovestone: Communist, Anticommunist, and Spymaster, 1999
    - Early printed writings by Lovestone, 1927-1937. (Folder 15: 5)
      Includes "America Facing Europe," 1927; America Prepares the Next War, 1928; 1928: The Presidential Election and the Workers, 1928; The Labor Lieutenants of American Imperialism; What Next for American Labor? 1934; Soviet Foreign Policy and the World Revolution, 1935; People's Front Illusion: From "Social Fascism" to the "People's Front," 1937; The American Labor Movement: Its Past, Present and Future; and New Frontiers for Labor
  - Maghreb region (North Africa), 1989-1993. (Folder 15: 6)
    Includes Congrès Constitutif de l'Union Syndicale des Travailleurs du Maghreb Arabe, 1989; and Charte des droits sociaux fondamentaux des travailleurs du Maghreb Arabe, 1991
  - Mali, 1970-1971. (Folder 15: 7)
    Includes "Cité d'Ouvriers Workers Housing Project, Sogoninnko, Mali," (AALC project proposal), 1970
  - Meany, George (president, AFL-CIO), 1950-1980 (Folder 15: 8)
  - Morocco, 1989-1996. (Folder 15: 9)
    Includes reports of the national congress of the Union Marocaine du Travail, 1989
  - National Endowment for Democracy, 1987-2008. (Folder 16: 1)
    Includes performance reviews and audit reports
  - Organization of African Trade Union Unity, 1965-1986 (Folder 16: 2)
  - Palestine, 1977-1996. (Folder 16: 3)
    Includes report on trade unions in the West Bank and Gaza, 1996
  - Philippines, 1993 (Folder 16: 4)
  - Randolph, A. Philip (president, Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters), 1975-1992 (Folder 16: 5)
  - Ross, Michael (director, AFL-CIO Department of International Affairs), 2003-2007 (Folder 16: 6)
  - Rustin, Bayard (president, A. Philip Randolph Institute), 1977-1993 (Folder 16: 7)
  - Saudi Arabia. Ahmed Subhy Mansour, "The Religious Sunni Opposition in the Saudi Kingdom in the 20th Century," (holograph), 2002 (Folder 16: 8)
  - Shanker, Albert (president, American Federation of Teachers), 1997 (Folder 16: 9)
  - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr (Soviet dissident novelist), 1975 (Folder 16: 10)
  - South Africa (Box 16)
    - AALC internal memoranda and working materials, 1975-1996. (Folder 16: 11)
      Includes AFL-CIO Program of Action in South Africa, 1990 (AALC report); "Management Assessment and Evaluation Report: South Africa Labor Union Assistance," 1990 (U.S. Agency for International Development report); "Democratic Transition in South Africa," 1991 (draft AFL-CIO Executive Council statement); and evaluation report of AALC programs in South Africa, 1995
    - Collected material, 1985-2007. (Folder 16: 12)
      Includes ANC: The Inside Story, circa 1985 (pamphlet); "Conditions in South African Jails," 1986 (International Confederation of Free Trade Unions report); Workers' World, 1993 (International Labour Research and Information Group magazine issues); Breaking Boundaries, 1994 (Congress of South African Trade Unions pamphlet); and Jani Roberts, "Glitter and Greed: The Diamond Investigation," 2001 (Internet article)
  - Soviet Union, 1980-1999. (Folder 17: 1)
    Includes Boris Shelomov, How Soviet Trade Unions Look after Workers' Interests, 1982 (Soviet pamphlet); The International Department of the CC CPSU under Dobrynin, 1988 (U.S. Foreign Service Institute report); and proceedings (in French) of plenary session of the All-Union Central Council of Trade Unions of the Soviet Union, 1989
  - Springer, Maida (African-American labor activist), 1999-2000. (Folder 17: 2)
    Includes Yevette Richards, "Race, Gender, and Anticommunism in the International Labor Movement: The Pan-African Connections of Maida Springer," 1999 (Internet article)
  - Stand, Kurt (East German spy), 1997-2000. (Folder 17: 3)
    Relates to Kurt Stand-Theresa Squillacote-James Clark espionage case
  - Sudan, 1990 (Folder 17: 4)
  - Switzerland, 1984 (Folder 17: 5)
  - Togo, 1987 (Folder 17: 6)
  - Tunisia, 1959-2006. (Box 17)
    - General. Includes Le Peuple, 1959 (Union Générale Tunisienne du Travail special magazine issue); Irving Brown memorandum on establishment of an AALC regional office for northern Africa in Tunis, 1970; and Juliette Bessis, Farhat Hached, 1977 (Jeune Afrique special supplement) (Folder 17: 7)
    - Tlili, Ahmed. Includes photocopies of letters by Tlili, 1966-1967; and Lettre à Bourguiba, 1988 (posthumous pamphlet by Tlili) (Folder 17: 8)
  - Washington Area Labor Committee on Central America and the Caribbean, 1986 (Folder 17: 9)
  - Weiner, Herbert E. (U.S. Department of State labor attaché), 1954-2007. (Folder 17: 10)
    Includes interview transcript, printed article by Weiner, and obituary
  - World Federation of Trade Unions (Box 17)
    - General, 1985-2006. (Folder 17: 11)
      Includes AFL-CIO and International Confederation of Free Trade Unions internal memoranda and working materials relating to the WFTU
    - Continuity and Change: The World Federation of Trade Unions and International Labor Unity, 1988 (AFL-CIO Free Trade Union Institute report) (Folder 18: 1)
    - World Congress (10th: 1982: Havana). Printed pictorial report (Folder 18: 2)
    - General Council session (41st: 1988: New Delhi). Proceedings (Folder 18: 3)
    - World Congress (12th: 1990: Moscow). Proceedings (Folder 18: 4)
    - World Congress (15th: 2005: Havana). Reports and summaries (Folder 18: 5)
    - Flashes from the Trade Unions (WFTU publication), 1987-1993 (Folder 18: 6)
    - World Trade Union Movement (WFTU publication) (Box 18)
      - 1986 (Folder 18: 7)
      - 1987 (Folder 19: 1)
      - 1988 (Folder 19: 2)
      - 1989 (Folder 19: 3)
      - 1990 (Folder 19: 4)
    - Miscellaneous WFTU issuances, 1984-2005. (Folder 19: 5)
      Includes African Trade Unions and Foreign Debt, (pamphlet) 1987
  - Worldwide Labor Officers' Conference (2005: Washington). Conference materials. Includes "A Labor Diplomacy Strategy for the Muslim World" (report of the Advisory Committee on Labor Diplomacy) (Folder 19: 6)
  - Zambia, circa 1991 (Folder 19: 7)
  - Miscellany, 1992-2007 (Folder 19: 8)
- Audiovisual File, circa 1910s-2000s. (Box 20)
  Photographs, audiotapes, and videotapes, arranged by physical form
  - Photographs. Depicts American, African and other international labor leaders, and scenes at World Assembly of Youth, International Labour Organisation, International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, AFL-CIO, African-American Labor Center, and other events, circa 1910s-2000s (Box 20)
    - Numerically keyed photographs, with individual numbers on the back of each photograph, and keyed individual descriptions arranged by number. Individuals depicted include I. W. Abel, Bella Abzug, Habib Achour, Omer Becu, Mahjoud Benseddik, Bill Bradley, David Brombart, Irving Brown, Abdou Diouf, Enzo Friso, Hubert H. Humphrey, John T. Joyce, Thomas Kahn, Andrew Kailembo, Edward Kennedy, Lane Kirkland, George Meany, Jay Naidoo, Patrick O'Farrell, Yuri Orlov, William Rogers, Maida Springer, Margaret Thatcher, Ahmed Tlili, John Vanderveken, and David Wirmark (Folder 20: 1)
    - Captioned photographs. Individuals depicted include Cyrille Adoula, David Brombart, Irving Brown, Elmer Cope, Arthur Deakin, Dwight Eisenhower, Alfred Gruenther, Jay Lovestone, George Meany, Robert Murphy, A. Philip Randolph, Walter Reuther, Michael Ross, Walther Schevenels, Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, and Vincent Tewson (Folder 20: 2)
    - Captioned photographs. Individuals depicted include David Brombart, George W. Bush, Arthur Deakin, Samuel Gompers, William Green, Léon Jouhaux, Walter Reuther, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Tran Quoc Buu, and Emile Vandervelde (Folder 20: 3)
    - Uncaptioned photographs of Irving Brown and others. Other individuals depicted include Arnold Beichman, David Brombart, David Dubinsky, Jerry Funk, Jacob Javits, Jay Lovestone, George Meany, Daniel Moynihan, Nguyen Cao Ky, Richard M. Nixon, Walter Reuther, William Rogers, and Maida Springer (Folder 20: 4)
    - Uncaptioned photographs of George Meany and others. Other individuals depicted include Habib Achour, David Brombart, John F. Kennedy, and Walter Reuther (Folder 20: 5)
    - Uncaptioned photographs of Lane Kirkland and others. Other individuals depicted include David Brombart, Jay Naidoo, and Yuri Orlov (Folder 20: 6)
    - Uncaptioned photographs. Individuals depicted include Kofi Annan, James Baker, Arnold Beichman, David Brombart, Abdou Diouf, David Dubinsky, Jerry Funk, Samuel Gompers, William Green, Hubert H. Humphrey, John T. Joyce, Thomas Kahn, Patrick O'Farrell, Yuri Orlov, Frances Perkins, A. Philip Randolph, Walter Reuther, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Bayard Rustin, and Leonard Woodcock (Folder 20: 7)
    - Uncaptioned photographs of David Brombart and others (Folder 20: 8)
    - World Assembly of Youth photographs, circa 1950s-1960s. (Folder 20: 9)
      Individuals depicted include David Brombart, Jawaharlal Nehru, and David Wirmark
    - Zambian election observation photographs, 1991 (Folder 20: 10)
      Individuals depicted include David Brombart and Jimmy Carter
  - Audiotapes (Box 21)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D. Speech excerpts, 1933-1945 (Box 21)
    - Kirkland, Lane. Eulogy at George Meany funeral, 1980 (Box 21)
  - Videotapes (Box 21)
    - Worldnet French-language television program featuring David Brombart, 1989 (Box 21)
    - Force Ouvrière May Day celebration, Paris, France, featuring Marc Blondel and David Brombart, 1996 (Box 21)
    - Memorial service for Lane Kirkland, Washington, D.C., 1999 (Box 21)
- Memorabilia, undated. (Box 22-23)
  Convention badges, lapel pins, and assorted commemorative items
- Oversize File, 1952-1990. (Box 24)
  Oversize memorabilia, serial issues, and photograph
  - Framed mementos, 1968-1990 (Box 24)
  - Oversize serial issues including articles on the American labor movement and Irving Brown, 1957-1970 (Box 24)
  - Plaque commemorating International Labour Organisation conference, 1976 (Box 25)
  - Fortieth anniversary reproduction of International Confederation of Free Trade Unions manifesto, 1989 (Box 25)
  - Revue WAY bound volume, (World Assembly of Youth French-language newspaper), 1957-1961 (Box 25)
  - Oversize photograph of International Confederation of Free Trade Unions dinner, 1952 (Box 25)
- World Assembly of Youth File II, 1958-1964 (Box 26)
  Issuances of the World Assembly of Youth
  - Bound volume of printed reports and resolutions, and issues of Appel à l'action, 1958-1964. (Folder 26: 1)
  - Bound volume of reports and conference proceedings, 1962. (Folder 26: 2)
  - Bound volume of reports and conference proceedings, 1963-1964. (Folder 26: 3)
- International Labour Organization File II, 1974 (Box 27: 1)
  Journal article
- Subject File II, 1965-2009 (Box 27)
  Conference proceedings, clippings, printed articles, and serial issues, arranged alphabetically by topic
  - Cuba
    - Assisting Independent Trade Unions in Cuba Conference, Washington, D.C., Briefing book, 2009 (Folder 27: 2)
    - Cuba sindical. Serial issue, 2008 (Folder 27: 3)
  - Labor and intelligence, 1965-1969. (Folder 27: 4-5)
    Clippings and journal articles relating to connections between the AFL-CIO and the U.S. Central Intelligence Agency
  - Mozambique, Newspaper issue, 1988 (Folder 27: 6)